<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Quantum Information]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>site-lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>Quantum Information</title><link></link></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 22:05:26 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="site-lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 22:05:02 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator></dc:creator><item><title><![CDATA[Surface Code]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Planar (2D) lattice structures are suitable for practical realizations of topological <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Quantum Error Correction" data-href="Quantum Error Correction" href="quantum-error-correction.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">QER</a> codes.
Planar surface code hosting one logical qubit: No periodic boundary conditions!<br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20250823124916.jpg" src="images/pasted-image-20250823124916.jpg" target="_self"> Logical () operators need to start over opposite smooth (rough) boundaries of the lattice respectively.
Thus these are non-contractible strings starting and ending at boundaries (topological property)
They fulfill the anticommutation relation and commute with all stabilizers.
4-qubit plaquette and vector stabilizers in the bulk
Reduced 3-qubit -type and -type stabilizers at the smooth and rough boundaries
Minimal surface codes of distance (one arbitrary error correctable):<br><img alt="Pasted image 20250823125659.jpg" src="images/pasted-image-20250823125659.jpg" target="_self">]]></description><link>surface-code.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Surface Code.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2025 10:57:00 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250823125659]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250823125659.jpg" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250823125659.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250823125659.jpg</guid><pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2025 10:56:58 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250823124916]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250823124916.jpg" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250823124916.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250823124916.jpg</guid><pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2025 10:49:16 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Quantum Error Correction]]></title><description><![CDATA[The error rates of Quantum computation applications for guaranteed quantum advantage in the fault taulerant regime needed are . This is why Quantum Error Correction is very important in the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Route to large-scale fault tolerant quantum computing.canvas" data-href="Route to large-scale fault tolerant quantum computing.canvas" href="route-to-large-scale-fault-tolerant-quantum-computing.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Route to large-scale fault tolerant quantum computing</a>. The coupling to the environment causes decoherence, for example magnetic field fluctuations. Dephasing can happen in a mixed state in an open system simulated by pure coherent superposition states, which leads to the loss of phase information. Other than that <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="X Gate" data-href="X Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/x-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">X-errors</a>, <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Y Gate" data-href="Y Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/y-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Y-errors</a> and <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Z Gate" data-href="Z Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/z-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Z-errors</a> could happen as well as leakage and qubit loss.In classical error correction redundancies are introduced, for example n-bit repetition code, with majority vote as correction strategy. The repetition code fails if more than half of the bits suffer errors (bit flips).<br>Redundancy can not work in the quantum case due to the <a data-href="No-Cloning Theorem" href="no-cloning-theorem.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">No-Cloning Theorem</a>. Also we can't directly measure quantum states to find out about the errors that occurred. This leads to a collapse of the wave function., information about and lost ().
even worse for entangled states by measuring one of the qubits only (). Measuring a single qubit collapses the state!Errors in quantum information are intrinsically continuous (rather than discrete):
Example: Undesired perturbation Hamiltonian The effective error model we use in the following are stochastic, independently distributed (uncorrelated) X,Y,Z errors with probability .<br>By constructing <a data-href="logical qubits" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">logical qubits</a> a quantum repetition code can be constructed such as the <a data-href="3-qubit code" href="3-qubit-code.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">3-qubit code</a>. The code can detect errors and correct errors.Stabilizer states are a set of commuting observables which allow to describe a large class of multi-qubit states including all QEC codes considered here.
Example: Bell states are stabilizer states, e.g.: Stabilizers and is a unique 2-qubit state for which All stabilizers commute and span a dimensional Abelian group. The Stabilizer state is uniquely fixed to by imposing for . The stabilizers span the n-dimensional subspace which is called the codespace. Also logical operators and can be defined which fulfill the following: Logical operators need to commute with the stabilizers, , and mutually anticommute, . Essentially one counts the number of anticommutes and if its even, hen it commutes otherwise it anticommutes.
A distance- QEC code can correct errors.
A distance- QEC code can detect errors.
There exist weight- errors that directly induce an (undetectable) logical error<br>
Generally QEC doesn‘t account for every single qubit error which is bound by the <a data-href="Quantum Hamming Bound" href="quantum-hamming-bound.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Quantum Hamming Bound</a>
<br>These codes can concatenated, the advantage is that the failure probability of logical qubits gets exponentially suppressed as the system size increases. Assuming the gate error probability is the failure probability for the 'th layer is . One example of such concatenation of the 3-qubit code is the <a data-href="9-qubit Shor code" href="9-qubit-shor-code.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">9-qubit Shor code</a>. Other than that larger codes have a higher success probability. For an n-code with <a data-href="distance" href="distance.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">distance</a> which is the minimal <a data-href="weight" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">weight</a> the error probability scales with for small . The <a data-href="Quantum Threshold Theorem" href="quantum-threshold-theorem.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Quantum Threshold Theorem</a> assumes that every component can fail and guarantees an error probability where arbitrary quantum computations can be performed efficiently. In practice the error threshold are very demanding ().Idea:
topology = robust global features which are invariant under local changes or perturbations
assumption: noise and errors act locally
Store quantum information spread out globally to protect it against noise
The error thresholds are about and fault tolerant QC might be possible in practice! To what topological QEC codes are can be seen in .<br>
Examples are the <a data-href="Kitaev‘s toric code" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Kitaev‘s toric code</a> and the <a data-href="Surface Code" href="surface-code.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Surface Code</a>.
]]></description><link>quantum-error-correction.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Error Correction.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2025 10:48:54 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Kitaev's toric code]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Most commonly studied and experimentally pursued topological <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Quantum Error Correction" data-href="Quantum Error Correction" href="quantum-error-correction.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">QEC</a> code (experimental variant: „surface code“) square lattice with physical qubits located on the edges:<br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20250812101449.jpg" src="images/pasted-image-20250812101449.jpg" target="_self">
The vertices are a star operator and correspond to the action of the two qubits around them
<br>All <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Quantum Error Correction > Stabilizer formalism" data-href="Quantum Error Correction#Stabilizer formalism" href="quantum-error-correction.html#Stabilizer formalism" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">stabilizers</a> mutually commute: , because plaquette and vertex operators share zero or two qubits (even number of anticommutes)
They define the codespace: Here we consider lattice with periodic boundary conditions, i.e. embedded on the surface of a torus toric code
The number of logical qubits can be determined by counting the number of physical qubits and independent constraints: plaquettes physical qubits (they re on the edges) plaquettes Z-stabilizers vertices X-stabilizers
However, not all stabilizers are independent, the -th stabilizer is redundant: Only independent X,Z-stabilizersThis yields for The toric code can host 2 encoded logical qubits. This is a topological property, and independent of the lattice size or lattice structure (square lattice, hexagonal lattice, etc.)Logical operators correspond to non.contractable string operators winding around the hole and the handle of the torus:<br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20250812144047.jpg" src="images/pasted-image-20250812144047.jpg" target="_self"><br><img alt="Pasted image 20250812144133.jpg" src="images/pasted-image-20250812144133.jpg" target="_self">
All string operators commute with all stabilizers: and touch an even number of vertices, the first half and last half of the vertex is combined to one full vertex in the torus and touch an even number of plaquettes and of the same encoded qubit anticommute as required: They share exactly one single physical qubit and thus the number of anticommutes is uneven Logical operators of different needed qubits commute as required: thus Note that logical operators don‘t have unique qubit support (which means that they do not reach any arbitrary qubit normally) but can be deformed by multiplication with stabilizer operators which act trivially on logical states:
<br><img alt="Pasted image 20250813102404.jpg" src="images/pasted-image-20250813102404.jpg" target="_self">
The deformed operators have the same action on logical states:
Commutation and anticommutation relations are preserved under such continuous deformations:<br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20250813103016.jpg" src="images/pasted-image-20250813103016.jpg" target="_self">Finally, one can write the logical basis states explicitly in the Z-Basis:Intuitively the following happens: We maximize the deformations of the strings, we can change the order of the terms because the logical operators commute with the stabilizers. The string could be deformed again generally. But in this case the state is the eigenstate for the projector of the -basis for all qubits, so we get an eigenvalue +1 for those projectors, so only the projectors remain. Remember that the last stabilizer is redundant and doesn‘t change the subspace of the projectors, meaning that the eigenvalues of the stabilizers already have been considered.
Example L=2:
<br>Errors on physical qubit show up as stabilizer „excitations“ (i.e. <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="indirect measurement" data-href="indirect measurement" href="indirect-measurement.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">-1 eigenvalue measurements</a>) of adjacent plaquette and vertex operators:
Idea: Syndrome information is used to make best possible guess about the homological class of the set of errors which have occurred on the system Errors are created randomly and can diffuse
We want to detect the errors quickly and reliably, and keep them localized and remove them <br><img alt="Pasted image 20250813172432.jpg" src="images/pasted-image-20250813172432.jpg" target="_self"><br><img alt="Pasted image 20250813172634.jpg" src="images/pasted-image-20250813172634.jpg" target="_self"><br>The error correction succeeds iff the loop (Correction attempt + Error chain ) is a contractable loop. Note, that the error chain is unknown. This is equivalent to a concatenation of <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Quantum Error Correction > Stabilizer formalism" data-href="Quantum Error Correction#Stabilizer formalism" href="quantum-error-correction.html#Stabilizer formalism" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">stabilizer</a> operators which don‘t change the codespace per definition. A non contractable loop leads to a logical operation equivalent to a logical error.
Independently distributed, stochastic bit and phase flip errors on physical qubits occurring with probability can be corrected as long as .
Decoding (i.e. determining a correction attempt given an error syndrome) an be done e.g. using the minimum-weight matching (MWPM) algorithm: find correction chain with overall shortest length<br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20250813173558.jpg" src="images/pasted-image-20250813173558.jpg" target="_self">
<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Surface Code" data-href="Surface Code" href="surface-code.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Planar surface codes</a> are the physical implementation for the toric code.]]></description><link>kitaev&apos;s-toric-code.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Kitaev&apos;s toric code.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2025 10:47:56 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Protocols]]></title><description><![CDATA[
entangled state example bell state
how to construct how would one create an entangled state QPE
No-cloning Theorem and Proof
how to construct Name a universal gate set
How many gates are needed to construct n-qubit unitary what is a rotation gate show on bloch sphere
enough to get to arbitrary rotations?
enough for universality? is entangled? yes
draw circuit is CNOT, H universal? how to make it universal?
given arbitrary U is it efficient to decompose into CNOT H T, complexity?
classical computing nand
toffoli quantum cnot toffoli universality universal set
produce X from T H CNOT reversible vs irreversible
classical &amp; quantum computing why nand impossible in quantum examples for reversible
CNOT from toffoli can you entangle with swap gate? why? Grover Algorithm circuit + explain oracle how the speedup are (if one does not now calculate)
Hammin bound formula
order finding
Draw order finding circuit given some numbers what is the order
how to factor a number using r Bernstein Vazirani circuit
compare classic/quantum oracle NP hard problems how to speed up? Grover
geometric picture what is the probability after k steps Deutsch Josza explain objective problem
oracle
circuit
how to measure (projective measurement) Vazirani Scaling quantum vs classical QFT 1 qubit
2 qubit
n qubit gate count definition of R_n QPE What are codes and why one needs it?
states losing coherence toric code stabilizer circuit Explain Steane Code with logical operators + sketch non disturbing measurement
9 qubit code how many logical qubit
how many error corrected
stabilizers
what happens iff certain error happens
how to correct error
how to measure indirectly
is circuit fault tolerant?
what is the weight of the error Color Code (Steane)
distance 3 surface code stabilizers
how to measure
error propagation, show uncorrectable error Stabilizer codes minimum qubits for 1 logical 1 arbitrary error
5 qubits
write down stabilizers for that Quantum hamming bond
error propagation
order finding shor circuit
derive factors Color code
toric code
3 qubit code p_corr graph how to decrease concatatenation
how much improvement General stuff/ less about formulas, writes complex formulas himself and lets you explain them
We use the notation now: observation test (instead of POVM)
effect/observation (instead of effect operator)
transformations (instad of kraus operators/ canonical coarse graining form) pure transformation is one kraus operator Correspondence between superoperators and bipartite operators (instead of Choi-Jamiolkowski)
Deterministic preparation= Normalized state Probabilistic preparation test =Sub-normalized states collected into an ensemble
Probabilistic observation test = Effects collected into a positive-operator-valued-measure (POVM), destructive measurement
Deterministic transformation = Channel or evolution Probabilistic transformation test = Operations collected into an instrument, measurement, transformation-valued measure POVM Effect operator identity+ Pretty good Operator
Effect operators and POVM and how they relate to each other effectors do not give the state after measurement and how to compute the probability.
constraints (semipositivity, sum to unitary) construct a Pretty good measurement from 3 point in the blochsphere
how to prepare an ensemble
how to calculate probability in open system
what are requirements on transformatioin (CP preserving) show that it is cp preserving do a canonicial form of use steering to get canonical A-basis open systems definition
what does transformkation do to a state
represent pure state in canonical basis
dreive kraus oeprators from circuits and example
constraints of transformation test
open systems experiment definition#
transformation conditions does isometric transformation increase/decrease dimension of system
closed system definition Quantum Channel 1/2(X X + Z Z) apply on blochsphere representation =&gt; calculation
Distinguishing non-orthogonal states prove, that measurement operators can not perfectly distinguish non-orthogonal states steering explain
what about commincation
causality steering
steering
how to define transfomation properties subunit trace preserving completely positive or enough when only positive? completely positive marginal operators?
definition entanglement processing 4 rules what is entanglement dimension in bipartite system
definition entanglement processing 4 rules how to simulate remote transformation by local transformation? show
canonical form of observations and states no information without disturbance
Information = Disturbance: What does this mean
writes down formula, show what the objects are (Measurement and Superoperator)
"No disturbance without communication"
"No disturbance means no information" Deriving Measurement Operators from Evolution and Choi-Jamiolkowski
Explain entanglement supping Explain
what is upper limit (1/)
show that Cauchy Schwartz use write down maximally entangled state
swap operation trafo not valid entanglement swapping circuit
write down teleportation Information = Disturbance
information=disturbance
what is a non informative transf test what are proportion? information=disturbance
bob and alice quantum teleportation
signalling without communication Entangled states Example: Bell state
Is entangled? (Yes, draw circuit) Constructing entangled states Quantum gates and universality Name a universal gate set
Is CNOT + H universal? How to make it universal
Gates needed for an n-qubit unitary: Arbitrary decomposition into CNOT, H, T Rotation gates Bloch sphere representation
Arbitrary rotations and universality Classical vs quantum computing NAND, Toffoli, CNOT
Reversible vs irreversible
Why NAND impossible in quantum
Examples of reversible operations
Can you entangle with SWAP? Why? No-cloning theorem Proof Quantum Phase Estimation (QPE) Grover’s algorithm Circuit and oracle
Speedup explanation (geometric probability) Hamming bound formula
Order finding Circuit
How to factor using the order Bernstein-Vazirani Circuit and comparison with classical oracle Deutsch-Jozsa Objective/problem, oracle, circuit
Measurement (projective) NP-hard problems Grover speedup Quantum Fourier Transform (QFT) 1, 2, n-qubit versions
Gate counts
Definition of Quantum error correction Why codes are needed (coherence loss)
Stabilizer circuits, Steane Code 9-qubit code Logical qubits, error correction, stabilizers
Error propagation, indirect measurement, fault tolerance, error weight Color code (Steane)
Distance-3 surface code
3-qubit code, concatenation, error probability improvement
Minimum qubits for 1 logical qubit correcting arbitrary error (5-qubit code) Shor’s algorithm Order finding, circuit, factor derivation Notation Observation test (POVM)
Effect/effect operator
Transformation (instead of Kraus operator)
Deterministic vs probabilistic preparation and observation POVM &amp; effect operators Constraints: semipositivity, sum to identity
Pretty Good Measurement (PGM) example with 3 Bloch points State preparation and ensembles
Open systems Definition, pure vs mixed states, canonical basis
Transformation effects on states, Kraus operators from circuits
Conditions: , CP-preserving Isometric transformations System dimension Quantum channels Example: on Bloch sphere Distinguishing non-orthogonal states (impossibility proof)
Steering Communication, causality
Simulating remote transformation via local operations Canonical form of states and observations
Entanglement processing Definition, rules, entanglement dimension No information without disturbance Meaning, formulas (measurement and superoperator)
Teleportation, entanglement swapping circuits Non-informative transformation tests
Entanglement swapping probabilities Upper limit , proof using Cauchy-Schwarz Maximally entangled states
]]></description><link>protocols.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Protocols.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2025 10:00:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250813173558]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250813173558.jpg" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250813173558.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250813173558.jpg</guid><pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 15:35:58 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250813172634]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250813172634.jpg" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250813172634.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250813172634.jpg</guid><pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 15:26:34 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250813172432]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250813172432.jpg" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250813172432.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250813172432.jpg</guid><pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 15:24:32 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250813103016]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250813103016.jpg" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250813103016.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250813103016.jpg</guid><pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 08:30:16 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250813102404]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250813102404.jpg" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250813102404.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250813102404.jpg</guid><pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 08:24:04 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[index]]></title><description><![CDATA[Welcome to My Quantum Information Notes. To get started use the search bar on left or the graph on the right.]]></description><link>index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">index.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 22:04:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Universality of Quantum Gates]]></title><description><![CDATA[There exist universal gate sets, from which any quantum circuit on n qubits can be built.CNOT + arbitrary single-qubit rotations = universalCNOT + small (finite) set of single qubit gates = universal
{CNOT, H, T}
They allow one to approximate an arbitrary n-qubit circuit to arbitrary precision
Arbitrary n-qubit gates can be decomposed into products of n-qubit unitary operators that act in a <a data-href="2-dimensional subspace" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">2-dimensional subspace</a> only.
Goal: Decompose n-qubit gate U into product of gates acting only with a unitary V on 2-dim subspace only:
(Rest of entries are zero) unitary,
Example d=3 for illustration purposes, We will find two-level unitaries such that If we manage, it follows that
and thus If are unitaries so are their inverses .If , set If , set Note: for both cases is a valid 2-level unitary
^
Now, one can check that With some other entries denoted by prime’.
The key property is that now the left middle entry is now zero due to constructionNext, we will achieve to set the lower left entry to zero:If , set If , set In either case we will find: is unitary thus Finally we set For d= :
We need to construct in general d-1 two-level matrices such that Then d-2 for the second column, etc.
In the end we manage to write the matrix by some two-level matrices , with For an n-qubit system it follows that U can be written by at most two-level matrices
Discussion:
This is inefficient (exponential to n)
For specific unitaries much more efficient decompositions may exist
There exist however matrices which can not be decomposed into less than an exponential number of two-level unitaries
Quantum computation and quantum algorithms are not about arbitrary unitaries, but realizing unitaries with a lot of structure which can be efficiently decomposed <br>Arbitrary such gates, acting only on two computational basis states in the -dimensional Hilbert space of n-qubits can be written in terms of <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="CNOT gate" data-href="CNOT gate" href="gates/two-qubit-gates/cnot-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">CNOT gates</a> and single-qubit <a data-href="Rotation Gates" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/rotation-gates/rotation-gates.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Rotation Gates</a>.<br>
Goal: Implement these two-level unitaries by <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="CNOT gate" data-href="CNOT gate" href="gates/two-qubit-gates/cnot-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">CNOT gates</a> and single qubit rotations only:
Example 1) unitary,
This acts non-trivially only on and . This means that V is applied to qubit 3 iff qubit 1 and 2 are in .
This Toffoli-type 3 qubit gates (n qubit gates) can be built from CNOT-gates and controlled-U gates only with :<br><img alt="Pasted image 20250722152918.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250722152918.png" target="_self"><br>And 2-qubit <a data-href="Controlled-U Gate" href="gates/two-qubit-gates/controlled-u-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Controlled-U Gate</a> operations can be built from CNOTs and suitable chosen single-qubit operations A,B,C for which and holds<br><img alt="Pasted image 20250722153750.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250722153750.png" target="_self">Every (Group of unitaries with determinant 1) can be written as and or those the one-qubit unitaries would be A general unitary V can be written as where has determinant 1 and is a phase this can be achieved by using a Phase gate after the control qubit<br>
Example <a data-href="Hadamard-Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/hadamard-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Hadamard-Gate</a> from iH Gate which can be realized through rotations<br><img alt="Pasted image 20250722160138.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250722160138.png" target="_self">
Example 2)Choose the last configuration and construct the unitary as such that it acts on that (Here ). Then note which other configuration it acts on (Here ). Then change one bit at a time from the start configuration (Here ) until you convert to said configuration it usually acts on (Here ). This is called Grey code which connects those states.With the following notation:<br><img alt="Pasted image 20250723101736.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250723101736.png" target="_self" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;">We get the following circuit for our grey code:<br><img alt="Pasted image 20250723103124.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250723103124.png" target="_self">To realize controlled-U operations in an efficient way, where one qubit undergoes U if n others are all in like in this picture:<br><img alt="Pasted image 20250723103523.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250723103523.png" target="_self" style="width: 200px; max-width: 100%;"><br>One can use <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Toffoli Gate" data-href="Toffoli Gate" href="gates/two-qubit-gates/toffoli-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Toffolis</a> to concatenate the control qubits to <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Ancilla" data-href="Ancilla" href="quantum-mechanics/ancilla.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ancillas</a>:<br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20250723110031.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250723110031.png" target="_self">Resource Count:
For one 2-level unitary we need at most controlled operations to implement the swap of basis states according to the Grey Code, i. e. of these operations
Resource requirement for such Toffolis. This amounts to single qubit and CNOT gates
We saw that we needed at most two-level unitaries to decompose the n-qubit unitary Implementation of an arbitrary n-qubit unitary U can be realized by a quantum circuit containing single-qubit and CNOT gates <br>Arbitrary single-qubit rotations can be approximated by a finite set of single-qubit gates (e.g. <a data-href="T-Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/t-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">T-Gate</a> and <a data-href="Hadamard-Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/hadamard-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Hadamard-Gate</a>)<br>
A concatenation of Rotations is another <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Rotation Gates" data-href="Rotation Gates" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/rotation-gates/rotation-gates.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Rotation</a> with an angle of an irrational multiple of in the Bloch sphere. Example: With is a transcendental equation, this means that is an irrational multiple of . That is why we never revisit the same point on the circle! We can get arbitrarily close to any point in the circle The circle is densely covered<br>
We can construct another orthogonal vector (which are linearly independent) with <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Hadamard-Gate" data-href="Hadamard-Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/hadamard-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">H-Gates</a>:
<br>
Where we used the identities of the Hadamard for <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="X Gate" data-href="X Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/x-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">X</a>,<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Y Gate" data-href="Y Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/y-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Y</a> and <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Z Gate" data-href="Z Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/z-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Z</a> Gates.
Arbitrary single-qubit rotations can be built up from rotations about two axes as:
<br> Thus, we can approximate an arbitrary single-qubit operation by only <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Hadamard-Gate" data-href="Hadamard-Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/hadamard-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">H</a> and <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="T-Gate" data-href="T-Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/t-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">T</a>.<br>
The efficiency of the approximation is given by the <a data-href="Solovay-Kitaev-Theorem" href="gates/solovay-kitaev-theorem.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Solovay-Kitaev-Theorem</a>. For a given small desired error , a few rotations are sufficient to quickly get close to the desired .<br>
Due to the <a data-href="Gottesmann-Knill theorem" href="gates/gottesmann-knill-theorem.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Gottesmann-Knill theorem</a> any <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Clifford Gates" data-href="Clifford Gates" href="gates/clifford-gates.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Clifford Gate</a> can be perfectly simulated efficiently.
]]></description><link>gates/universality-of-quantum-gates.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Universality of Quantum Gates.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 18:35:38 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250812144133]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250812144133.jpg" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250812144133.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250812144133.jpg</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 12:41:32 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250812144047]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250812144047.jpg" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250812144047.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250812144047.jpg</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 12:40:46 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Overview]]></title><description><![CDATA[BLOCK 1&nbsp;(tentative list of topics covered)1 - Overview and Introduction2 - Quantum Gates and Circuits3-A - Deutsch Algorithm3-B - Deutsch-Jozsa Algorithm and Bernstein-Vazirani Problem4 - Classical Computation
5 - Universality of Quantum Gates
6 - Computational Complexity
7 - Grover Quantum Search Algorithm
8 - Quantum Fourier Transform
9 - Quantum Phase Estimation
10 - Quantum Order Finding
11-A - Shor Algorithm for Factoring BLOCK 2Lecture 1 : Rules of Quantum Theory We formulate rules of quantum theory characterizing what is possible and what is not, making the role of information explicit.• For open quantum ”systems” some information got lost : Non-pure events / circuits require a mathematically more complicated description which is, however, closer to an operational understanding of what goes on in the physics lab and to classical theory• For closed quantum ”systems” there is no information that can get lost : Pure events allow a mathematically simpler description which is, however, not directly related to the physics in the lab or classical theoryWe explore several ways these two formalisms are related. The goal is to master both and to be able switch between them at will.The quantum rules mathematically contruct probabilities from Hilbert-space vectors/operators subject to a physical contraint of causality. But other than this, the rules of quantum theory are simply mathematically postulated without any deeper physical motivation beyond “experiments conﬁrm their predictions”. This leaves us to “discover the physics” by solving operational tasks of information processing. This is what Lecture 2-5 do systematically.Terminology State vectors, density operators, ensembles, POVMs, channels, operations, instruments, isometries, non-orthogonal setsLecture 2 : Observations on Preparations With the quantum rules in hand we ﬁrst study the simplest quantum circuit where a single system A is prepared and then observations are performed to extract information contained in their joint probabilities : We verify that the closed-system rules indeed only describe pure preparations based on the simulatability of the probability distributions that they can generate, and likewise for observations. We then analyze non-pure preparations of open systems by bringing these into a standard simulation form, identifying what is “quantum” about them, and likewise for observations : • Non-pure preparations are always mixtures with information encoded in the probabilities of mixing (like classically) but also in the freedom of choice of the pure states that are being mixed (unlike classically)• Non-pure observation are always coarse-grainings involving pure observations (like classically) but the freedom of choosing these prohibits the simulation of any measurement by post-processing of a single pure observation device (unlike classically)This “Non-uniqueness of prepation reﬁnement” and “No post-processings of ideal measurement” turn out to be the same thing.
We then analyze 2 basic tasks of information extraction :
• In tomography, we extract complete information characterizing an unknown preparation by a D-outcome observation on the quantum system• In perfectly distinguishing, a known set of preparations is identiﬁed by a d-outcome observation device without extracting complete information about these states(“Which one is it?”)(“Which of these is it)These task are related by D=d 2 expressing an “information gap” : Tomography is quadratically harder than perfectly distinguishing This is the operational signiﬁcance of the quantum rule “States are d×d positive matrices on a Hilbert space”Terminology Measurement in orthogonal basis, IC-POVMs Lecture 3 : Steering a pure preparationWe next consider a quantum circuit where two systems are jointly prepared. A local measurement is performed to extract information from one system B and we investigate what classical communication B→A implies for the description of the other remote system A
With communication, this results in remote steering.
steeringThe solution of this operational task leads to a characterization of all pure, correlated states These correlations are not simulatable by coarse-graining of coordinated local preparations (unlike classically)
Without communication there is no remote eﬀect as dictated by causality.
The solution of the inverse operational task, puriﬁcation, leads to a pure, correlated simulation of any remote non-pure state of an open system (classically impossible). The “non-uniqueness of mixture reﬁnement of preparation” of Lecture 2 is fully characterized.
The non-locality of entanglement is shown to limited by the locality of quantum tomography, the ability to characterize any quantum state by local observations (like classically): Entanglement is monogamous correlation, non-shareable by more than 2 parties
Terminology Entanglement, Schmidt decomposition of bipartite vectors, SVD, partial traceBLOCK 3&nbsp;(tentative list of topics covered)
12-A - Basic Concepts of Quantum Error Correction
12-B - Stabiliser Formalism and Complete Codes
13-A - Introduction to Topological QEC Codes
13-B - Fault-Tolerant Universal Gates and Scalable ArchitecturesBLOCK 4Lecture 4-5 systematically performs the analogous steps of Lecture 2-3 for transformations (measurements, evolutions) thereby completing the framework of essential results of quantum information theory :Lecture 4 : TransformationsThe next level of complexity is a quantum circuit involving transformations of the preparation of a single system. These can extract information about input state A before a further, ﬁnal observation is made on the disturbed output state B : We verify that the closed-system rules indeed only describe pure transformations by the simulatability of the probability distributions that they generate. The purity of the identity transformation (“trivially doing nothing”) implies that nontrivial result that information-extraction implies disturbance of a quantum system, starting from clear-cut deﬁnitions based on probabilities in the lab. We analyze non-pure transformations of open systems by again bringing them into a standard simulation form and we identify what is “quantum” about them : • A non-pure transformation is always a coarse-grainings of some pure “transition” processes (like in classical theory) but there is freedom of choice in which “transitions” are coarse-grained (unlike classical theory)• A non-pure transformation need not be a mixture (like classical theory)This “non-uniqueness of reﬁnement” of transformations is remiscent of that of for states. This is no coincidence :
We again analyze 2 basic tasks of information extraction :
• Tomography, extracting complete information characterizing an unknown transformation, turns out to be possible by “encoding” the transformation in its modiﬁcation of pure entangled state and “decoding” it by using the corresponding state as resource for teleportation of input to output• Perfectly distinguishing a known set of transformations likewise turns out to be possible by perfectly distinguishing these corresponding states(“Which one is it?”)(“Which of these is it?”)The uncovered preparation-transformation correspondence is a key trick that allows to convert any result about preparations into a result about transformations and vice versa. This is systematically exploited in the ﬁnal lecture.Terminology Kraus operators, (Sudarshan-)Kraus theorem, (de Pillis-)Choi-Jamiolkowski correpondence, HEWJ theorem Lecture 5 : Steering a pure transformationFinally, the most complex quantum circuit we need to consider involves transformations jointly preparing two output systems AB taking input from one system C. A local measurement is applied to extract information from one output B and we investigate what classical communication B→A implies for the transformation outputting to the remote system A :steering
With communication, this results in remote transformation steering.
The solution of this operational task leads to characterization of pure entanglement generating transformations
Without communication there is no remote eﬀect as dictated by causality.
The solution of the inverse operational task, transformation puriﬁcation, leads to a pure simulation of any non-pure transformation with remote output (classically impossible). The “nonuniqueness of transformation reﬁnement” in Lecture 4 is fully characterized.
The non-locality of entanglement generation is likewise shown to limited by the locality of quantum tomography : Entanglement is monogamous correlation, non-shareable by more than 2 parties.
Terminology Schmidt decomposition of isometries, Stinespring dilation, channels, operations, instrumentsWhat will we learn ?By systematically analyzing very basic operational tasks allowed by the rules of quantum theory and switching back and fort between closed- and open-system formalisms, we will derive all essential results in quantum information theory. In doing so, we illustrate :Quantum theory is all about information. Quantum circuits are the calculations.We stress that all the results can be –and often are– derived in mathematical style and discussed in purely mathematical language. This is not wrong, but it does leave the reader interested in physics to ﬁgure out what it is all about.However, we will see time and again that the mathematics naturally follows from the operational physics. This is not a coincidence : All of the mathematics of quantum theory (ﬁnite dimension, without superselection) can be derived by solving the information processing tasks discussed in this lecture, starting from a few operational deﬁnitions and manipulating quantum circuits.BLOCK 11.1 Circuit identities (few simple identities/rules)
1.2 SWAP gates (proof of swap gates and implementation from cnot, does swap gate create entanglement)
1.3 Deutsch algorithm (implementation)
1.4 Deutsch Josza algorithm (implementation)
2.1 Bernstein Vazirani (implementation)
2.3 Controlled-U gates )(controlled U Gate construction from single qubit unitaries)
3.1 n-controlled U gates (Implementation via controlled Vs, logical expression equivalent)
3.2 Grover 2-bit (Implementation)
3.3 Grover 3-bit (Implementation and optimal k)
4.1 Phase estimation (Alternative iterative approach)
4.2 Single qubit measurements on multipartite states (creation of GHZ and W-state with circuits)
4.3 Decomposition of multi qubit unitaries (Implementation of grey code)
5.1 Magic state and T-state injection
5.2 Shor‘s algorithm (Doing algorithm per hand)
5.3 Universal gate sets (alternative gate sets)BLOCK 26.1 Physical validity of mathematical expressions
6.2&nbsp;Ensemble tomography with orthogonal measurements 7.1 Conclusively distinguishing distinct states
7.3 Tomographic preparation device8.1 Conclusively distinguishing – Implementations10.1 Basic qubit “noise” channels BLOCK 310.2 Quantum Error Correction (QEC) with a 7-Qubit Steane Code (How works and constructing other logical gates (e.g. ))11.1 Quantum error correction of qubit loss (How it works and implementation)Block 412.1 Correspondence Bell states ↔ Pauli transformations
12.2 Teleportation and communication]]></description><link>overview.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Overview.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 10:06:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Later notes]]></title><description><![CDATA[To make a transformation deterministic one can introduce an <a data-href="Ancilla" href="quantum-mechanics/ancilla.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ancilla</a> which flags or encodes the success or fail probability.
]]></description><link>later-notes.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Later notes.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 09:23:06 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250812101449]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250812101449.jpg" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250812101449.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250812101449.jpg</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 08:14:48 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Quantum Threshold Theorem]]></title><description><![CDATA[There exists a physical error probability below which arbitrary and a bunch of ancilla qubits quantum computations can be performed efficiently.]]></description><link>quantum-threshold-theorem.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Threshold Theorem.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 08:11:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[9-qubit Shor code]]></title><description><![CDATA[It is a code based on the concatenation of the 3-qubit repetition code in the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Z Gate" data-href="Z Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/z-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Z-</a> and <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="X Gate" data-href="X Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/x-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">X-Basis</a>:<br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20250811180916.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250811180916.png" target="_self">
Explicit form of logical state:
Bit flip errors are corrected by measuring -stabilizers: Phase flip errors are detected by measuring -stabilizers Properties:
Complete code: arbitrary error correctable
Degenerate code: several errors (e.g. and and ) have the same effect on logical states.
Correction works if: correction attempt+ error=identity or a stabilizer <br>not-perfect/optimal: <a data-href="Quantum Hamming Bound" href="quantum-hamming-bound.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Quantum Hamming Bound</a> says , thus the stabilizers span a subspace higher than needed in theory
]]></description><link>9-qubit-shor-code.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">9-qubit Shor code.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 16:34:22 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250811180916]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250811180916.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250811180916.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250811180916.png</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 16:09:16 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Quantum Hamming Bound]]></title><description><![CDATA[How large must a Hilbert space be, so that one can accommodate a QEC code that fulfills the following conditions?
n qubits, encoded qubits, error correction works for up to errors.
Reasoning: For errors, there are possible locations, 3 types of errors (), thus a total number of possible errors The code space is -dimensional and each error is required to map the codespace to an -dim. Orthogonal subspace. All these subspace need to fit in the -dim. Hilbert space:
For 1 logical qubit (), 1 arbitrary correctable error (), this particularizes to: qubits needed for smallest complete code, with stabilizers and logical operators ( are cyclic permuations) ]]></description><link>quantum-hamming-bound.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Hamming Bound.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 15:52:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[distance]]></title><description><![CDATA[The code distance is the smallest <a data-href="weight" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">weight</a> i.e. the number of physical qubits that a logical operator has support on.]]></description><link>distance.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">distance.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 15:02:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[3-qubit code]]></title><description><![CDATA[Distribute an arbitrary quantum state over an entangled state of physical qubits. Encode logical qubit:
Basis states or codewords span the codespace, a subspace of the Hilbert space, in which arbitrary logical superpositions live: Encoding: quantum circuit Use two <a data-href="Ancilla" href="quantum-mechanics/ancilla.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ancilla</a> qubits initialized in :<br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20250810181304.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250810181304.png" target="_self" style="width: 400px; max-width: 100%;"> Possible occurrence of errors:
E.g. bit flip error on qubit 1: How can we find out about the error that occurred on the system? Direct measurement of all qubits would collapse the state into or : Information about and would be lost.
<br>Solution: we realize an <a data-href="indirect measurement" href="indirect-measurement.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">indirect measurement</a>, using additional ancilla qubits and syndromes (measurements) and <br><img alt="Pasted image 20250811152057.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250811152057.png" target="_self"> No information gained about the encoded state ( and coefficients) Strategy corrects up to one -error on any qubit
2 simultaneous errors induce a logical bit flip error
Example error: QER fails
For 3 simultaneous errors : is not detectable and directly induces a logical bit flip error.
Phase flip errors, e.g. also is undetectable and directly induces a logical phase flip error. 3-qubit code is not a complete code.The probability to correct error(s) is the following:
<br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20250811154800.jpg" src="images/pasted-image-20250811154800.jpg" target="_self">Here for , , thus better protection offered by 3-qubit code.The 3-qubit code can be formulated as a stabilizer QEC code:<br><img alt="Pasted image 20250811163959.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250811163959.png" target="_self">The logical operators are and ]]></description><link>3-qubit-code.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">3-qubit code.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 14:41:58 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250811163959]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250811163959.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250811163959.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250811163959.png</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 14:39:58 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250811154800]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250811154800.jpg" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250811154800.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250811154800.jpg</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 13:48:00 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250811152220]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250811152220.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250811152220.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250811152220.png</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 13:22:20 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250811152203]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250811152203.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250811152203.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250811152203.png</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 13:22:02 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250811152149]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250811152149.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250811152149.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250811152149.png</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 13:21:48 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250811152057]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250811152057.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250811152057.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250811152057.png</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 13:20:56 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250811151949]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250811151949.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250811151949.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250811151949.png</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 13:19:48 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[indirect measurement]]></title><description><![CDATA[An indirect measurement can be achieved by the following construction:
Consider a unitary (n-qubit)operator with eigenvalues .
<img alt="Pasted image 20250811142111.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250811142111.png" target="_self" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;"> are projection operators on the eigenspaces of Realizes a measurement of The projectors share a common eigenbasis with U by construction and commute. The states of the codespace span the subspace and thus always the -state is measured with certainty. The elements outside the codespace (errors) span the subspace and thus always the -state is measured.In the 3-qubit code for unitary the following circuit can be used to do an indirect measurement:<br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20250811151031.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250811151031.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>indirect-measurement.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">indirect measurement.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 13:11:12 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250811151031]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250811151031.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250811151031.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250811151031.png</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 13:10:30 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250811142111]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250811142111.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250811142111.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250811142111.png</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 12:21:10 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Grover]]></title><description><![CDATA[The quantum search algorithm was proposed by Lev Grover in 1994.
Search through a search space of N elements.
Assume for convenience n bits of information to label one element
Assume that the problem of interest has exactly solutions (typically ) How fast can we find at least one of the solutions?
A particular instance of a problem is conveniently represented by a function , which takes as an input an integer , , and yields if is a solution to the search problem if is not a solution to the search problem
Hamiltonian path problem:
A particular graph specifies .
Inputs correspond to paths (i.e. sequences of vertices)
$$
f(x) = \begin{cases}
1 &amp; \text{if } x \text{ is a Hamiltonian path in } G \
0 &amp; \text{otherwise}
\end{cases}\begin{align}
| \Psi \rangle &amp;= \frac{1}{\sqrt{N}} \sum_x | x\rangle = \frac{1}{\sqrt{N}} \left(\sum^{’’} |x \rangle + \sum^{’} |x \rangle \right) \
&amp;= \frac{1}{\sqrt{N}} \left(\sqrt{N-M} \frac{1}{\sqrt{N-M}} \sum^{’’} |x \rangle + \sqrt{M} \frac{1}{\sqrt{M}} \sum^{’} |x \rangle \right) \
&amp;= \sqrt{\frac{N-M}{N}} | \alpha \rangle + \sqrt{\frac{M}{N}} | \beta \rangle \
&amp;= \sqrt{1-\varepsilon} | \alpha \rangle + \sqrt{\varepsilon} | \beta \rangle
\end{align}\begin{align}
O | \psi \rangle &amp;= O(\sqrt{1-\varepsilon} | \alpha \rangle + \sqrt{\varepsilon} | \beta \rangle) \
&amp;= \sqrt{1-\varepsilon} | \alpha \rangle - \sqrt{\varepsilon} | \beta \rangle \
&amp;= (\sqrt{1-\varepsilon} | \alpha \rangle + \sqrt{\varepsilon} | \beta \rangle)- 2\sqrt{\varepsilon} | \beta \rangle \
&amp;= |\psi \rangle - 2 \sqrt{\varepsilon} | \beta \rangle \
UO |\psi \rangle &amp;= (2 |\psi \rangle \langle \psi | - \mathbb{I})(|\psi \rangle - 2 \sqrt{\varepsilon} | \beta \rangle) \
&amp;= 2 |\psi \rangle - |\psi \rangle - 4 \sqrt{\varepsilon} \langle \psi|\beta\rangle |\psi \rangle + 2\sqrt{\varepsilon} |\beta \rangle \
&amp;= (1-4 \varepsilon)|\psi \rangle+2\sqrt{\varepsilon} | \beta \rangle \
&amp;= (1-4\varepsilon) (\sqrt{1-\varepsilon} | \alpha \rangle + \sqrt{\varepsilon} | \beta \rangle)+2\sqrt{\varepsilon} | \beta \rangle \
&amp;= (1-4 \varepsilon) \sqrt{1-\varepsilon} |\alpha \rangle + \sqrt{\varepsilon}(3-4 \varepsilon)|\beta \rangle
\end{align}\begin{align}
p_\mathrm{fail} &amp;= \cos\left({\frac{2k+1}{2}\theta}\right)^2 \
&amp;= \cos\left({\frac{2\tilde{k}+1}{2}\theta} + (k-\tilde{k}) \theta \right)^2 \
&amp;= \cos\left(\frac{\pi}{2} + (k-\tilde{k}) \theta \right)^2 \
&amp;= \sin\left((k-\tilde{k}) \theta \right)^2 \
&amp;\leq \sin\left(\frac{\theta}{2}\right)^2
\mathrm{for} , |k-\tilde{k}| \leq \frac{1}{2}, \mathrm{and} , \theta \ll 1 \
&amp;= \frac{M}{N} ; \mathrm{small}
\end{align}]]></description><link>algorithms/grover.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Algorithms/Grover.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Aug 2025 17:13:34 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Deutsch]]></title><description><![CDATA[The Deutsch Algorithm was developed by David Deutsch (1992). This was the first algorithm that showed the potential computational power of quantum computation.
The Algorithm demonstrates typical features and ingredients of quantum computation for example <a data-href="Quantum Superposition" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Quantum Superposition</a> and <a data-href="Quantum Entanglement" href="quantum-mechanics/quantum-entanglement.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Quantum Entanglement</a>.
Consider a single bit A black box that computes a function We do not know (and do not care) how, but every evaluation of f is extremely costly (e. g. in terms of computational time) Thus, we want to limit the number of evaluations of f to an absolute minimum 4 possibilities
So there are two cases:
: f is constant, all bits are the same.
or
: f is balanced, half of the bits are 0, the other half 1.We are not interested in the individual values of and but only in the global property whether f is constant or balanced.
First compute individual values and . We get more information than we need, namely on the individual values.
In a second step we compare the two values We need two evaluations Claim: We can do better, with a single evaluation of f. We won‘t (in fact must not) obtain any information on the individual values of f, yet we will be able to answer the question
We will use two qubits, in an initial product state We will use a two-qubit unitary transformation Here denotes addition modulo 2 The transformation leaves the first qubit unchanged and acts on the second one as follows: If y is not changed
If y is flipped Remarks: After the transformation, the state can not be written as a product state: is unitary and Hermitian because Every application of requires one evaluation of f For we get: This state contains both functions in superposition in the second qubit and in general entangled with the first qubit
If we measure the first qubit the second qubit collapses to either or with probability 1/2. This is not better than one evaluation in a classical algorithm because we get to know the both individual values (with uncertainty). It is even worse.<br> <a data-href="Quantum Parallelism" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Quantum Parallelism</a> is an ingredient for speedup but not enough. We also need <a data-href="Algorithmic Interference" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Algorithmic Interference</a>, i. e. a way of constructively interfering the paths such that the information we are interested in (f balanced or constant) is amplified, and the information we don‘t care about (individual values and ) becomes inaccessible. If we prepare the -state we get the following: For we get: So the first qubit is measured as for a constant function and for a balanced function The information of the individual function values appear as a global phase factor () which can not be measured directly. Final Step: measurement the probability of the -state is 1 for f constant the probability of the -state is 1 for f balanced <br>
With specific preparation of and an <a data-href="Oracle" href="algorithms/oracle.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Oracle</a> which is an implementation of Remarks: We evaluated f only once
<br>Speedup due to <a data-href="Quantum Parallelism" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Quantum Parallelism</a> is 2 (Constant) <br><img alt="Deutsch.png" src="images/deutsch.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>algorithms/deutsch.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Algorithms/Deutsch.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Aug 2025 16:40:58 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="images/deutsch.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;images/deutsch.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250810181304]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250810181304.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250810181304.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250810181304.png</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Aug 2025 16:13:04 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No-Cloning Theorem]]></title><description><![CDATA[There exists no physical procedure to copy any arbitrary quantum state Proof:
Imagine that such an operation exists, which performs the following map:Consider two input states and : Take the inner product: which is only true, if and are either equal or orthogonal We can't copy states and that are not orthogonal.]]></description><link>no-cloning-theorem.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">No-Cloning Theorem.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Aug 2025 14:41:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Route to large-scale fault tolerant quantum computing]]></title><description><![CDATA[Layer 5: Application
Quantum algorithms and interface to classical userLayer 4: Logical
Construct a substrate supporting universal quantum computationLayer 3: Quantum error correction
QER corrects arbitrary system errors if rate is below thresholdLayer 2: Virtual
Open-loop error cancellation such as dynamic decouplingLayer 1: Physical
Hardware apparatus including physical qubits and control operations]]></description><link>route-to-large-scale-fault-tolerant-quantum-computing.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Route to large-scale fault tolerant quantum computing.canvas</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Aug 2025 13:35:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Quantum Fourier Transform]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Input: length-N vector of complex numbers Output: transformed data Definition of FT: Inverse FT (using <a data-href="Kronecker Delta" href="math/kronecker-delta.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Kronecker Delta</a> identity):Example: For : For arbitrary : Unitary matrix:Costs:
Naively: steps (multiplication and addition) per entry, thus for length-N vector
More efficient: Fast Fourier Transform (FFT), takes. Only steps.
QFT acts on orthonormal basis states :Thus, the action on an arbitrary input stateIn the following we will consider , with are computational basis states of n qubits.
A state can be written in binary representation as , which stands forE.g.: : We will also use the binary fraction notationUseful Identity:The action of the QFT on a ground state is the following:This is a product state, no entanglement is created. In the exponential not all terms are important, as integer multiples of will lead simply to a factor of 1:Only the last binary digits of matter.<br> can be generated by a <a data-href="Rz gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/rotation-gates/rz-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Rz gate</a> up to a global phase: . Example: (first part Hadamard, second part is a phase drift on qubit 2, depending on ) (first part Hadamard, second part depending on , third part depending on ) <br><img alt="Pasted image 20250727174859.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250727174859.png" target="_self"><br>The <a data-href="SWAP Gate" href="gates/two-qubit-gates/swap-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">SWAP Gate</a> at the end ensures that the qubit order is consistent. Those are not necessary though.<br><img alt="Pasted image 20250727180256.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250727180256.png" target="_self">Resources:
<br> <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Hadamard-Gate" data-href="Hadamard-Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/hadamard-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Hadamard-Gates</a> <br> conditional rotations (2 <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="CNOT gate" data-href="CNOT gate" href="gates/two-qubit-gates/cnot-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">CNOTs</a> each)
At most swap gates (3 CNOTs each) Quantum Algorithm
Comparison: Best classical algorithm FFT requires gates. QFT provides an exponential speedup
Note:
The QFT is not an algorithm to speed up the computation of classical Fourier transforms.
Problem:
No way known to access the amplitudes in a quantum computer directly
No way now to efficiently prepare original state to be transformed<br>
But: QFT is a key ingredient in other quantum algorithms like <a data-href="Quantum Phase Estimation" href="algorithms/quantum-phase-estimation.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Quantum Phase Estimation</a>.
]]></description><link>algorithms/quantum-fourier-transform.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Algorithms/Quantum Fourier Transform.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 09 Aug 2025 07:04:22 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Rz gate]]></title><description><![CDATA[The Rz Gate is one of the <a data-href="Rotation Gates" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/rotation-gates/rotation-gates.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Rotation Gates</a>. The Ry gate is a single-qubit rotation through angle &nbsp;(radians) around the z-axis.version 1.0
qubits 2
H q[0] # execute Hadamard gate on qubit 0
Rz q[0],-1.12 # rotation around z-axis of -1.12 radians on qubit 0
]]></description><link>gates/single-qubit-gates/rotation-gates/rz-gate.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Single-qubit gates/Rotation Gates/Rz gate.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 09 Aug 2025 06:54:54 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Quantum teleportation]]></title><link>quantum-teleportation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum teleportation.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 13:06:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Observations on Preperations]]></title><description><![CDATA[The joint probability is the conditional times the marginal probability. The marginal probability of preparation equals the operator trace norm, while the conditional observation probability is obtained using deterministic state with trace-normalized operator. A preperation device is deterministic (probabilistic) with outcome(s), iff its marginal probability = .
<img alt="Pasted image 20250804162428.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250804162428.png" target="_self">Normalization of a preparation by post-selection reverses the information flow to / from the lab. This makes the probabilistic device deterministic by changing the outcome to the device label. This means that we wait until the prepared state that is wanted gets triggered. To obtain the deterministic preperation one needs to trace-normalize . This describes the conditional probabilities of any later observation .By discarding outcomes we automatically discard the device , eliminating any functional dependence of on this future choice<br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20250804164601.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250804164601.png" target="_self">It is also possible to coarse-grain over all outcomes to create a deterministic preparation device. Here two outcomes is reduced to one outcome.
Discarding preparation outcomes effectively defines a new deterministic preperation device. The effective deterministic preperation describes the probabilities generated by any choice of later observation <br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20250804165224.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250804165224.png" target="_self">
Preparation probabilities of the reining pure preparations (eigenvalues of operator )<br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20250805175341.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250805175341.png" target="_self">
The number of refining preparations that contribute with (rank of operator ) The subspace spanned by these orthogonal eigenvectors (support space of operator ) Every preperation (operator) has a canonical coarse-graining simulation (diagonal form with subnormalized eigenvectors). Here we use orthogonal covectors ().<br><img alt="Pasted image 20250805150155.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250805150155.png" target="_self">Thus we can see that the open-system quantum rules are the coarse-graining of closed-system rules (for preperations) can be simulated through coarse-graining with It can also be simulated through coarse-graining with Every preparation (operator) has a canonical simulation as a mixture which is the diagonal form with normalized eigenvectors.For the eigenvectors are and . Their observations are just because they are per definition orthonormal thus perfectly distinguishable. ]]></description><link>quantum-mechanics/observations-on-preperations.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Observations on Preperations.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 16:22:40 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250805175341]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250805175341.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250805175341.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250805175341.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 15:53:40 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250805164800]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250805164800.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250805164800.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250805164800.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 14:48:00 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250805150155]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250805150155.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250805150155.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250805150155.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 13:01:54 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250805150052]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250805150052.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250805150052.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250805150052.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 13:00:52 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250805145916]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250805145916.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250805145916.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250805145916.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 12:59:16 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Rules of Quantum Theory]]></title><description><![CDATA[In quantum theory switching between systems is always possible.through purifying and coarse graining respectively.<img alt="Pasted image 20250729131634.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250729131634.png" target="_self">Open quantum systems are obtained from closed quantum systems by discarding information.An Operational Circuit is directed from right to left and contain no loops. It is drawn as equations are written. It represents the joint probability of outcomes of an experiment as function of the events. All events jointly combine the probability of one possible set of outcomes (zyx) of the experiment. Orthogonal (co)vectors are denoted by the symbol .Rounded boxes Events
Single wires Quantum Systems
Double Wires Classical information about outcomes in the lab frameBoxes in time (in series) are connected by single wires (same lab frame) and boxes in space (in parallel) are not connected by single wires (different lab frames)A complete process involving the composition of quantum events that produce outcomes across multiple spatially separated laboratories, where each lab is accessible to agents who can communicate and condition or control their future choice of quantum operations or measurement devices based on prior information. Devices (or events they produce) are distinguished by their number of input and output quantum systems<br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20250729130522.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250729130522.png" target="_self">An&nbsp;event&nbsp;is a specific outcome resulting from one use of a device (like a measurement or operation), chosen among several possible alternatives, and fully described in terms of what happened in the lab during that operation. Preparations are also called states collected into ensembles, are also called Effects collected into positive-operator-valued-measures, POVMs)<br><img alt="Pasted image 20250729132150.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250729132150.png" target="_self">Quantum Theory is operationally defined by assigning mathematical objects to the systems Operational Quantity by a set rules () together with a rule to compute probabilities in the lab frame directly from these objects .
There are three probabilistic concepts important for these rules (not specific to quantum theory):
Probabilistic Deterministic: Number of outcomes (outgoing )
Conditioning outcome Conditioned choice: Outcomes Incomes (outgoing )
Non-pure Mixed: Probabilistic simulation with/out conditioning?
These concepts are all effected by coarse graining.
The devices are distinguished by the number of possible set of events (outcomes) that they produce in the lab. A deterministic device only produces one event (thus is omitted) while a probabilistic device have at least two possible events (thus is needed to specify). The deterministic device is not providing new information to the system. Those devices are indicated by a hat (e.g. )<br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20250729135334.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250729135334.png" target="_self">Coarse Graining (denoted by the „garbage bin“ at the end of the double arrow) over all possible events of a probabilistic device produces (or simulates) a deterministic device. The coarse grained device generates the probabilities of the probabilistic device summed over the discarded outcomes. Discarding a system means discarding all outcomes of any observation test performed on it<br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20250729140112.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250729140112.png" target="_self">Agents in the lab frame can choose which devices to use in a circuit during a experiment. Once a possible outcome has been chosen and run it collapses into that path. Conditioned choices are noted by an up arrow and a conditioning bar for probabilistic devices. For deterministic devices the conditioning bar is not necessary and only the device label is noted.<br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20250729140952.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250729140952.png" target="_self">Outcomes produced probabilistically can be used to condition other devices, this is a simulation of a new device which jointly produces all the outcomes.<br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20250729141731.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250729141731.png" target="_self">A pure event is an elementary event which has no underlying non-trivial probabilistic explanation. A pure event can not be simulated non-trivially. The purity of devices is the only operational assumption distinguishing the closed and open system quantum rules. Thus for pure events we use the notation for closed systems in the open system picture to indicate that. All pure events are Rank 1 projectors ( or Number of non-zero eigenvalues=1). Operators can only describe pure transformations!
E.g. for preparation (This is similar for transformations and observations): <br><img alt="Pasted image 20250729150634.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250729150634.png" target="_self">Example: can not be written as a probabilistic composition other than itself () and has a rank of 1 and is thus pure but can be written as a probabilistic composition of other preparations () and is thus non-pure. The rank is also 2.Devices that are mixed are always also non-pure, but not all non-pure events are mixed (except for preperations)! A mixed device can be simulated by coarse graining of device choices conditioned on a random variable. Thus the event is not mixed if the probabilities adding up are greater than one (). Example: is a mixed preperation. And as shown before on-pure. is not mixed because 1+1=2. This is also non-pure because the rank is 2. Thus this observation is neither pure nor mixed.<br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20250730173216.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250730173216.png" target="_self">
Note: To check operators against other operators (e.g. ) you check the eigenvalues against each other(e.g. ). There is no deterministic observation in the closed system. <br>Pretty good constructions reversing the causal order (, ) are indicated by overbar . The probabilities for the pretty good experiments are the same as for the original experiment. Mind that the order of devices don‘t change and use that the <a data-href="Trace" href="math/trace.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Trace</a> is cyclic and the rules for complex conjugate in the braket formalism. In the open system the probabilities and in the closed system the amplitudes stay the same for .
Open systems: With assumed invertible Closed systems: With assumed invertible <br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20250804144140.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250804144140.png" target="_self">Perfectly distingushable preparations and observations are the only ones equal to their adjoint pretty good construction. So preparations and observations seem only the same if one assumes perfect distinguishability]]></description><link>quantum-mechanics/rules-of-quantum-theory.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Rules of Quantum Theory.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 14:55:12 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250804165224]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250804165224.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250804165224.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250804165224.png</guid><pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 14:52:24 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250804164601]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250804164601.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250804164601.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250804164601.png</guid><pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 14:46:00 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250804162428]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250804162428.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250804162428.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250804162428.png</guid><pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 14:24:28 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250804144140]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250804144140.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250804144140.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250804144140.png</guid><pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 12:41:40 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Trace]]></title><description><![CDATA[The trace of any operator is the sum of diagonal elements in any orthonormal basis.
The trace has cyclic properties: The trace equals the sum of diagonal elements in any complete set of vectors
The partial trace is calculated as follows:
]]></description><link>math/trace.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Trace.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 12:29:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250730173216]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250730173216.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250730173216.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250730173216.png</guid><pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 15:32:16 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250729150634]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250729150634.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250729150634.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250729150634.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 13:06:34 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250729141731]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250729141731.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250729141731.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250729141731.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 12:17:30 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250729140952]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250729140952.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250729140952.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250729140952.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 12:09:52 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250729140112]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250729140112.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250729140112.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250729140112.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 12:01:12 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250729135334]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250729135334.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250729135334.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250729135334.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 11:53:34 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250729132150]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250729132150.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250729132150.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250729132150.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 11:21:50 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250729131634]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250729131634.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250729131634.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250729131634.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 11:16:34 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250729130522]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250729130522.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250729130522.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250729130522.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 11:05:22 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Quantum Phase Estimation]]></title><description><![CDATA[This makes use of <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Quantum Fourier Transform" data-href="Quantum Fourier Transform" href="algorithms/quantum-fourier-transform.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">QFT</a>.Suppose that a unitary has an eigenvector with eigenvalue , where is unknown.
The goal is to estimate (Note that ).
Assumptions: We have black boxes that prepare and peform controlled- operations, for suitable non-negative integers We will have two qubit registers: The first register contains qubits intitially in The choice of will depend on The desired number of digits of accuracy of the estimate of The desired success probability with which we wish the phase estimation procedure to be successful The second register begins in , containing as many qubits as are necessary to store <br>First we create an unbiased superposition by putting <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Hadamard-Gate" data-href="Hadamard-Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/hadamard-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">H-Gates</a> for all qubits for the first register. Then we do controlled- operations on the second register which is controlled by the th qubit on the first register. Consider one qubit of the first register, and All computational basis states are encoded in binary representation . Example: so the output state for t=4 k=3 is . The measurement of the qubits on the first register provides us exactly. Hadamard gates on all qubits of register 1
Controlled- operations on the second register, with raised to successive power of 2, controlled by the qubits of the first register
Apply the inverse QFT Measure the qubits of the first register in the computational basis In general can‘t be written exactly as binary -bit expansion
One can show that if one wants to get an approximate estimate for to an accuracy , and one wants the probability to obtain an estimate of this precision to be at least , one needs to choose the number of qubits in the first register as $$
t= n + \left[\log{\left(1+\frac{1}{2 \varepsilon}\right)}\right] <br>It is also possible to estimate the phase in an iterative process. First the following circuit with controlled by the ancillas is being applied with a measurement in the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="X Gate" data-href="X Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/x-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">X</a>-basis, for qubits 2,…,n additional unitaries controlled by the th classical bit given by the X-measurement are added before the measurement.]]></description><link>algorithms/quantum-phase-estimation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Algorithms/Quantum Phase Estimation.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 16:44:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[ShorΓÇÿs algorithm]]></title><description><![CDATA[
The problem of factoring: Given a positive composite integer number , what are the prime factors multiplied together equaling ?
A fast algorithm for order finding can be converted into a fast algorithm for factoring
Factoring is believed to be hard on classical computers: For an -bit integer , the best classical algorithms known to date (number field sieve) require roughly operations. This is exponential in the number of bits describing the number We can find a factor of if we find a non-trivial solution of . There are always two trivial solutions: and However if N is divisible by two distinct odd primes, these are at least two more non-trivial square roots in (i.e. among the set of numbers between 1 and , which are coprime with N):If , then neither nor is a multiple of . In that case, the greatest common divisors and must each be proper divisors of , i.e. prime factors we are looking for.
How can we find a non-trivial square root ? Choose a random integer , , check whether is coprime of . If it‘s not coprime, and share a prime factor, which we can easily find and we are done. If is coprime of , then run the <a data-href="Quantum Order Finding" href="algorithms/quantum-order-finding.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Quantum Order Finding</a> algorithm to find :In other words if we are lucky and the order is even, then is a square root of 1.
We know for sure that , since is the smallest integer for which this is true. If we are again lucky and too, then is a non-trivial root.
We then can calculate and to find non-trivial prime factors. Calculating gcd is efficient (Euclid‘s algorithm).
Choose e.g. order Check: 8 is a non-trivial square root of 1 in . and The number of elements of good coprimes where their order is even and can be determined in the following:If us divisible by distinct odd primes, then at least a fraction of the elements in are good. Thus, for , the probability to pick a good coprime is at least . We need only trials.Shor‘s quantum algorithm for factoring requires runs of the quantum algorithm for order finding. Overall runtime Compared to classical runtime Exponential speedup]]></description><link>algorithms/shorγçÿs-algorithm.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Algorithms/ShorΓÇÿs algorithm.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 16:28:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Clifford Gates]]></title><description><![CDATA[
All <a data-href="Pauli Gates" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/pauli-gates.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Pauli Gates</a> are Clifford Gates and the Generator of the Clifford Group: For n qubits one can construct the Pauli group: The n-qubit Clifford group is defined as the n qubit unitaries that normalize the Pauli Group: Note that this only applies for the entire set , not element-wise. Elements of the Clifford group are called Clifford gates. : Hadamard : The 16 Elements of are mapped onto But : , : :
- etc.<br>
The Clifford Gates can be generated by only. The <a data-href="Gottesmann-Knill theorem" href="gates/gottesmann-knill-theorem.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Gottesmann-Knill theorem</a> is an important result for efficiency of classical simulation of Clifford Gates.
The Clifford Group only reaches a discrete Set of the Bloch Sphere.
With the Universal Gate Set every point at the Bloch sphere can be reached.Discussion:
Hadamard and CNOT allow to create entangled states. This kind of entanglement alone does not provide an intrinsic quantum speedup!
Clifford Gates are not an universal gate set
Universal quantum computing requires at least one non-Clifford gate, e.g. the T-gate
Important quantum protocols involving only Clifford operations: <br><a data-href="Quantum teleportation" href="quantum-teleportation.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Quantum teleportation</a>
<br><a data-href="Magic state distillation" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Magic state distillation</a>
<br><a data-href="Quantum Error Correction" href="quantum-error-correction.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Quantum Error Correction</a> with stabilizer codes ]]></description><link>gates/clifford-gates.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Clifford Gates.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 16:14:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Classical Logic Gates]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Idealized or physical electronic devices that realize a Boolean function: a logical operation performed on one or more binary inputs ( FALSE/TRUE) that produce a single binary output
<img alt="Classical Gates.png" src="images/classical-gates.png" target="_self">There exists a minimal set of gates to implement any classical Boolean circuit. The set of gates are not unique, one example is {AND, NOT}. An example of a single gate that is universal is the NAND gate.The classical two-bit gates are essentially irreversible and non-invertible: for example from the output of the XOR gate, it is impossible to determine what the inputs a and b were. There is an irretrievable loss of information associated with the irreversible action of the XOR-gate, and other classical two-bit logic gates<br>The <a data-href="Toffoli Gate" href="gates/two-qubit-gates/toffoli-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Toffoli Gate</a> is reversible.]]></description><link>gates/classical-logic-gates.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Classical Logic Gates.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 16:14:12 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Deutsch-Josza]]></title><description><![CDATA[The Deutsch-Josza Algorithm is the multifunction generalization of the <a data-href="Deutsch" href="algorithms/deutsch.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Deutsch</a> Algorithm.
For N=, we are given an N-bit String as input such that either: all have the same value (“constant“) N/2 of the are 0, and are 1 (“balanced“) Here the index from to , to label all elements.
We can view this again as a function Goal: find out whether x is constant or balanced Note: We are not interested in the individual values , but only in the global property whether x is constant or balanced N=8, n=3 constant balanced
First compute individual values In this step we obtain more information than we need, namely on the individual values In a second step, we compare the values- A classical algorithm requires in general evaluations of x to answer the question (Worst case, if is the same as all before we know for certainty that the function is constant. With less evaluations we can only guess) Claim: we can do better, with a single evaluation of f. We won‘t (in fact must not) obtain any information on the individual values , if we will be able to answer the question <br>Many quantum algorithms work with queries (including <a data-href="Grover" href="algorithms/grover.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Grover</a> and <a data-href="Shor" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Shor</a>)
We can think of the inputs as an N-bit memory, which we can access at any point of our choice (RAM)
A memory access is via a so-called „black-box“, which outputs bit on input As a quantum operation, this is realized by the (n+1)-qubit unitary , with address register of n qubits target bit Remarks: After the transformation, the state is not necessarily a product state () , unless is one compuational basis state is unitary and hermitian because Every application of requires one evaluation of <br>We want to prepare an equal-weight superposition off all basis states on the first n qubits with <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Hadamard-Gate" data-href="Hadamard-Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/hadamard-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">H-Gates</a> If then we get The state contains all function values in superposition in the target qubit, and (in general) entangled with the first n qubits
<br>But we can access the information: If we measure the first qubits, the superposition collapses with probability to any computational state . This is not better than one evaluation in a classical algorithm. Similar to <a data-href="Deutsch" href="algorithms/deutsch.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Deutsch</a> we need <a data-href="Algorithmic Interference" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Algorithmic Interference</a> here. If then we get <br> (see <a data-href="Deutsch" href="algorithms/deutsch.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Deutsch</a>)
<br>So the action of the phase <a data-href="Oracle" href="algorithms/oracle.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Oracle</a> is which does nothing if and adds a phase if , the oracle can be thus noted as <br>Now we reapply <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Hadamard-Gate" data-href="Hadamard-Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/hadamard-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">H-Gates</a> and get the following in total: For is constant, our state is if all and if all because this is the only that survives. So if we measure this state we know for certainty that we have a constant function. If we measure a different state we know for certainty that we have a balanced function. We have again a global phase which is inaccessible which is important! The Deutsch-Josza algorithm can be solved with certainty using only one quantum query and other operations
In contrast any classical deterministic algorithm needs at least N/2 +1 queries Classical algorithm can solve this problem efficiently if we allow for a small error probability and can be in general better if we allow this It is identical to the Deutsch-Josza algorithm but with the additional property , the final measurement yields a with certainty
<br>Per definition of the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Hadamard-Gate" data-href="Hadamard-Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/hadamard-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">H-Gates</a> the following holds: After step (3) we have (with inserting ) Start with an register
Apply a Hadamard to end the qubit
Apply a phase oracle query Apply another Hadamard to each qubit
Measure the final state
<br><img alt="Deutsch-Josza.png" src="images/deutsch-josza.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>algorithms/deutsch-josza.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Algorithms/Deutsch-Josza.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 16:12:04 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="images/deutsch-josza.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;images/deutsch-josza.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Quantum Order Finding]]></title><description><![CDATA[
The problem of order finding is equivalent to factoring
We will develop an efficient quantum algorithm for order finding hoch in turn provides an efficient way to factor
The quantum algorithm for order finding will be using <a data-href="Quantum Phase Estimation" href="algorithms/quantum-phase-estimation.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Quantum Phase Estimation</a>
For positive integers and , , with no common factors (i.e. and are coprime) the order of modulo is defined to be the smallest integer , such that Example: order of 3 modulo 7 is This is then cyclic, if we continue: Since Order finding is believed (not proven!) To be a hard problem on a classical computerNo algorithm is known to solve the problem using resources that are polynomial in the bits needed to specify the problem, where is the number of bits needed to specify .
In essence, the quantum algorithm for order finding is the quantum phase estimation algorithm applied to the unitary , where is an -qubit state, Not that we are using the convention that when the expression .
In other words, acts non-trivially only when .
The following states are eigenstates of as shown below:We used and the fact that the term is the same as the term which allows us to shift the sum. Using phase estimation will allow is it obtain with high accuracy the corresponding eigenvalues from which we will be able to obtain the order with some extra work.
Problem: Preperation of would require knowledge about so this is impossible.<br>
However we don‘t need this since the superposition of all eigenstates (using the <a data-href="Kronecker Delta" href="math/kronecker-delta.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Kronecker Delta</a> identity):For each in the range 0 to this will lead an estimate of the phase that is accurate to bits, and with probability at least .For the algorithm to be efficient, we need efficient procedures to implement controlled -operations. This can be achieved by a technique called modular exponentiation.We need to realize the transformationThis can be achieved using reversible computing using temporarily a third register.
For that we compute by squaring up to . Since These are squaring operations.
Each requires operations (standard multiplication). operations which can be translated into a reversible quantum circuit with quantum gates which realizes The last step to get is using the Continued Fractions Algorithm whose use is allowed to the following theorem:
For a rational number such that then is a convergent of the continued fractions for , and thus can be calculated in steps.
Since is accurate to bits it follows since . Thus this theorem applies.Since . Thus the theorem applies.Express real numbers by integersImagine that and such that Imagine we have measured the outcome meaning Write as a continued fraction:Continued fraction algorithm requires steps.If we stop after 1 step: not " 2 steps: not " 3 steps: found The algorithm provides efficiently numbers .
The denominator is our candidate for the order .
We can check whether is the order by calculating , and if this is , we have found . Checking solutions in NP are always efficient.
<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Hadamard-Gate" data-href="Hadamard-Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/hadamard-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Hadamard-gates</a>: gates
<br>Inverse <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Quantum Fourier Transform" data-href="Quantum Fourier Transform" href="algorithms/quantum-fourier-transform.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">FT</a>: gates
Modular exponentiation: gates
Classical continued fraction algorithm: gates
Without proof: f the order finding attempt fails, one only needs to repeat a constant number of times to obtain the order r with high probability Overall cost , this can be reduced to almost by using known algorithms for fast integer multiplications modulo Inputs: Blackbox which performs for x being a coprime to the -bit number to be factored
Use qubits for the first register, prepared all in Prepare qubits the second register in the state Outputs: The order , i.e. the smallest integer for which Runtime: operations. Succeeds with probability Steps:
0. - initial state of and qubits superposition through Hadamards apply operations <br>apply inverse <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Quantum Fourier Transform" data-href="Quantum Fourier Transform" href="algorithms/quantum-fourier-transform.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">FT</a> to 1st register measure 1st register apply continued fraction algorithm <br>Factoring can be reduced to Order finding which is the most important ingredient in <a data-href="Shor‘s algorithm" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Shor‘s algorithm</a>]]></description><link>algorithms/quantum-order-finding.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Algorithms/Quantum Order Finding.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 16:10:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250727180256]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250727180256.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250727180256.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250727180256.png</guid><pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2025 16:02:56 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250727174859]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250727174859.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250727174859.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250727174859.png</guid><pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2025 15:48:58 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Kronecker Delta]]></title><description><![CDATA[The sum of all N N-th roots of 1 always are equal to one (except N=1).
<img alt="Pasted image 20250727155257.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250727155257.png" target="_self" style="width: 400px; max-width: 100%;">
That‘s why for the following holds:]]></description><link>math/kronecker-delta.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Kronecker Delta.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2025 13:57:56 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250727155257]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250727155257.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250727155257.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250727155257.png</guid><pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2025 13:52:56 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250726153118]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250726153118.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250726153118.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250726153118.png</guid><pubDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2025 13:31:18 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250726130507]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250726130507.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250726130507.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250726130507.png</guid><pubDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2025 11:05:06 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250726113705]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250726113705.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250726113705.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250726113705.png</guid><pubDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2025 09:37:04 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Oracle]]></title><description><![CDATA[The oracle does nothing with the state if it is the solution. If it is the solution it adds a Phase (for example -1). An oracle is a black box whose internal working are not important, the oracle has the ability to recognize the problem]]></description><link>algorithms/oracle.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Algorithms/Oracle.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2025 09:20:06 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Computational Complexity]]></title><description><![CDATA[Problems for which finding a solution can be achieved in time that scales polynomials with the size of the problem
Examples:
Eulerian Path Problem (Königsberg Bridge Problem)
Problems for which a solution can be found by a non-deterministic (N) Turing machine in polynomial (P) time.However, solutions can still be checked in polynomial time.Examples:
Hamiltonian Cycle Problem
Finding a needle in a haystack
Knapsack problem (NP-Complete)
Sudoku
A problem B is NP-complete, if for any problem A in NP there exists a polynomial-time reduction from A to BBounded-error quantum polynomial time is the class of decision problems solvable by a quantum computer in polynomial time, with an error probability of at most 1/3 for all instances.Examples:
<a data-href="Grover" href="algorithms/grover.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Grover</a>
<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Efficient Quantum Algorithms.canvas" data-href="Efficient Quantum Algorithms.canvas" href="efficient-quantum-algorithms.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Efficient Quantum Algorithms</a>]]></description><link>computational-complexity.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Computational Complexity.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2025 09:15:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Efficient Quantum Algorithms]]></title><description><![CDATA[NP problems BQP
NP-complete problemsP problems]]></description><link>efficient-quantum-algorithms.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Efficient Quantum Algorithms.canvas</guid><pubDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2025 09:13:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Quantum computer abstraction layers]]></title><description><![CDATA[SpecifiesConsist ofRealized throughAre applied toQ. Algorithms (e.g. <a data-href="Deutsch" href="algorithms/deutsch.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Deutsch</a>, <a data-href="Grover" href="algorithms/grover.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Grover</a>, <a data-href="Quantum Simulation" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Quantum Simulation</a>)<br>Quantum Gate sequences (e.g. <a data-href="CNOT gate" href="gates/two-qubit-gates/cnot-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">CNOT gate</a>, <a data-href="Toffoli Gate" href="gates/two-qubit-gates/toffoli-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Toffoli Gate</a>)<br>Basic system-specific operations (e.g. <a data-href="Rotation gates" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/rotation-gates/rotation-gates.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Rotation gates</a>)Control fields, pulses (e.g. lasers, EM-fields, phases)<br><a data-href="Physical qubits" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Physical qubits</a> (e.g. ions, atoms, photons, q. dots)]]></description><link>quantum-computer-abstraction-layers.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum computer abstraction layers.canvas</guid><pubDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2025 09:00:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Gottesmann-Knill theorem]]></title><description><![CDATA[Quantum circuits of only Clifford Gates can be perfectly simulated efficiently, i. e. in polynomial time, on classical computers.More precisely, circuits involving (i) preparation of qubits in computational basis, (ii) <a data-href="Clifford Gates" href="gates/clifford-gates.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Clifford Gates</a> and (iii) measurements in the computational basis.]]></description><link>gates/gottesmann-knill-theorem.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Gottesmann-Knill theorem.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2025 08:47:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pauli Gates]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a data-href="Identity Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/identity-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Identity Gate</a>, <a data-href="X Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/x-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">X Gate</a>, <a data-href="Y Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/y-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Y Gate</a> and <a data-href="Z Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/z-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Z Gate</a> are Pauli Gates.
]]></description><link>gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/pauli-gates.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Single-qubit gates/Pauli Gates/Pauli Gates.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 10:05:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Identity Gate]]></title><description><![CDATA[The Identity Gate is as follows:It does essentially nothing]]></description><link>gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/identity-gate.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Single-qubit gates/Pauli Gates/Identity Gate.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 10:05:06 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Solovay-Kitaev-Theorem]]></title><description><![CDATA[A single-qubit can be approximated to accuracy using gates from the discrete gate set. This is a poly-logarithmic increase- very slow (in particular not an exponential increase in ).]]></description><link>gates/solovay-kitaev-theorem.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Solovay-Kitaev-Theorem.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 10:01:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Rotation Gates]]></title><description><![CDATA[Rotation Gates can be built from <a data-href="Pauli Gates" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/pauli-gates.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Pauli Gates</a> like this:
With deconstructing the Pauli matrices in the Taylor representation the following holds:
<br>
An arbitrary rotation on the <a data-href="Bloch sphere" href="quantum-mechanics/bloch-sphere.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Bloch sphere</a> can be described as with .
Arbitrary single-qubit rotations can be built up from rotations about two axes as:
]]></description><link>gates/single-qubit-gates/rotation-gates/rotation-gates.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Single-qubit gates/Rotation Gates/Rotation Gates.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 09:53:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Z Gate]]></title><description><![CDATA[The Z Gate is as follows:The Z Gate can be built from the <a data-href="X Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/x-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">X Gate</a> and <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Hadamard-Gate" data-href="Hadamard-Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/hadamard-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Hadamard-Gates</a>:<br>It can also be built from <a data-href="Rz gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/rotation-gates/rz-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Rz gate</a>:
<br>The Z-Gate can also be built from the <a data-href="T-Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/t-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">T-Gate</a>:
qc.z(qr[0]) # execute Z-gate on qubit 0 ]]></description><link>gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/z-gate.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Single-qubit gates/Pauli Gates/Z Gate.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 09:50:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Bloch sphere]]></title><description><![CDATA[The Bloch sphere is a three dimensional representation of a two-level quantum mechanical system. The <a data-href="Hilbert Space" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Hilbert Space</a> is two dimensional and the representation is a sphere. Each point of outside and inside the sphere represents a valid state. The Sphere has a radius of 1.<br>
For qubits the North Pole of the sphere is the state, the South Pole the state. Those are the eigenstates of the <a data-href="Z Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/z-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Z Gate</a>. On the positive end of the x-axis the state is the - state, on the negative end the - state. Those are the eigenstates of the <a data-href="X Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/x-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">X Gate</a>. For the y-axis those are - state, on the negative end the - state. Those are the eigenstates of the <a data-href="Y Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/y-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Y Gate</a>. States on the surface of the Bloch sphere are <a data-href="Pure states" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Pure states</a>. States inside the Bloch sphere are <a data-href="Mixed States" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Mixed States</a>. The state in the origin of the Bloch sphere is a <a data-href="Maximally mixed state" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Maximally mixed state</a>.
A pure state in the Bloch sphere can be represented as follows: <br>Rotations on the Bloch sphere are realized by the <a data-href="Rotation Gates" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/rotation-gates/rotation-gates.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Rotation Gates</a>, which can transform any pure state into another states on the Bloch sphere. An arbitrary rotation can be described as with . <br><img alt="Bloch sphere.png" src="images/bloch-sphere.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>quantum-mechanics/bloch-sphere.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Bloch sphere.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 09:14:36 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Rx Gate]]></title><description><![CDATA[The Rx gate is one of the <a data-href="Rotation Gates" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/rotation-gates/rotation-gates.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Rotation Gates</a>. The Rx gate is a single-qubit rotation through angle&nbsp;&nbsp;(radians) around the x-axis.version 1.0
qubits 2
H q[0] # execute Hadamard gate on qubit 0
Rx q[0],-1.12 # rotation of -1.12 radians on qubit 0
]]></description><link>gates/single-qubit-gates/rotation-gates/rx-gate.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Single-qubit gates/Rotation Gates/Rx Gate.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 09:11:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250723110031]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250723110031.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250723110031.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250723110031.png</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 09:00:30 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[SWAP Gate]]></title><description><![CDATA[The swap gate swaps two qubits and can be constructed by a concatenation of <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="CNOT gate" data-href="CNOT gate" href="gates/two-qubit-gates/cnot-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">CNOTs</a>.<br><img alt="SWAP gate.png" src="images/swap-gate.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>gates/two-qubit-gates/swap-gate.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Two-qubit gates/SWAP Gate.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 08:47:10 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[CNOT gate]]></title><description><![CDATA[The CNOT gate (or Controlled-NOT gate) is two-qubit operation, where the first qubit is usually referred to as the control qubit and the second qubit as the target qubit. Expressed in basis states, the CNOT gate:
leaves the control qubit unchanged and performs a Pauli-X gate on the target qubit when the control qubit is in state&nbsp;;
leaves the target qubit unchanged when the control qubit is in state&nbsp;.
is equivalent to adding the value of the control qubit qubit to the value of the second qubit, and writing the result into the second qubit <img alt="Pasted image 20250723104636.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250723104636.png" target="_self" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;">qc.cx(qr[0], qr[1]) # execute CNOT gate with control qubit 0 and target qubit 1
]]></description><link>gates/two-qubit-gates/cnot-gate.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Two-qubit gates/CNOT gate.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 08:46:40 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250723104636]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250723104636.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250723104636.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250723104636.png</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 08:46:36 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[T-Gate]]></title><description><![CDATA[The T-Gate is as follows:The Phase Gate S can be built from the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="T-Gate" data-href="T-Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/t-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">T-Gates</a>: <br>The T-Gate is a specific <a data-href="Rz gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/rotation-gates/rz-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Rz gate</a>(up to phase):
qc.t(qr[0]) # execute Z gate on qubit 0
qc.tdg(qr[0]) # execute conjugate transpose of the T gate on qubit 0
]]></description><link>gates/single-qubit-gates/t-gate.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Single-qubit gates/T-Gate.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 08:42:34 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Phase-Gate]]></title><description><![CDATA[The Phase-Gate S is as follows:The Phase-Gate can be built from the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="T-Gate" data-href="T-Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/t-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">T-Gates</a>:qc.s(qr[0]) # execute phase gate on qubit 0
qc.sdg(qr[0]) # execute conjugate transpose of the S gate on qubit 0
]]></description><link>gates/single-qubit-gates/phase-gate.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Single-qubit gates/Phase-Gate.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 08:42:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Y Gate]]></title><description><![CDATA[The Y Gate is as follows:The Y Gate can be built from itself and <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Hadamard-Gate" data-href="Hadamard-Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/hadamard-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">H-Gates</a>:qc.y(qr[0]) # execute Y-gate on qubit 0 ]]></description><link>gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/y-gate.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Single-qubit gates/Pauli Gates/Y Gate.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 08:41:24 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[X Gate]]></title><description><![CDATA[The X Gate is as follows:The X Gate can be built from the <a data-href="Z Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/z-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Z Gate</a> and <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Hadamard-Gate" data-href="Hadamard-Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/hadamard-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">H-Gates</a>:qc.x(qr[0]) # execute X-gate on qubit 0 ]]></description><link>gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/x-gate.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Single-qubit gates/Pauli Gates/X Gate.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 08:41:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Ancilla]]></title><link>quantum-mechanics/ancilla.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Ancilla.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 08:38:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250723103523]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250723103523.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250723103523.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250723103523.png</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 08:35:22 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250723103124]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250723103124.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250723103124.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250723103124.png</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 08:31:24 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250723101736]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250723101736.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250723101736.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250723101736.png</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 08:17:36 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250722160138]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250722160138.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250722160138.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250722160138.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 14:01:38 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250722153750]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250722153750.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250722153750.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250722153750.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 13:37:50 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250722152918]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250722152918.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250722152918.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250722152918.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 13:29:18 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Toffoli Gate]]></title><description><![CDATA[The three-bit Toffoli Gate is a universal reversible logical gate: any reversible circuit can be built from Toffoli gates only. The NOT gate can be realized by and the AND gate by Its action is: Only if the first two input bits are set to 1, the gate inverts the third bit, otherwise the three bits remain all unchanged.Non trivial action: <img alt="Toffoli Gate.png" src="images/toffoli-gate.png" target="_self" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;">]]></description><link>gates/two-qubit-gates/toffoli-gate.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Two-qubit gates/Toffoli Gate.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 08:34:50 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Controlled-U Gate]]></title><description><![CDATA[U is applied to the second qubit if and only if the first qubit is in state . The <a data-href="CNOT gate" href="gates/two-qubit-gates/cnot-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">CNOT gate</a> is a Controlled-X Gate.<br><img alt="Controlled-U Gate.png" src="images/controlled-u-gate.png" target="_self" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;">]]></description><link>gates/two-qubit-gates/controlled-u-gate.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Two-qubit gates/Controlled-U Gate.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 08:34:38 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Controlled-U Gate]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/controlled-u-gate.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/controlled-u-gate.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Controlled-U Gate.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 08:34:18 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Toffoli Gate]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/toffoli-gate.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/toffoli-gate.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Toffoli Gate.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 08:25:26 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Classical Gates]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/classical-gates.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/classical-gates.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Classical Gates.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 08:11:42 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Deutsch-Josza]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/deutsch-josza.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/deutsch-josza.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Deutsch-Josza.png</guid><pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 16:29:12 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="images/deutsch-josza.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;images/deutsch-josza.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Hadamard-Gate]]></title><description><![CDATA[The Hadamard-Gate is as follows:The Hadamard Gate maps the Z-eigenstates to the X-Eigenstates and vice versa. The Hadamard Gate is unitary and hermitian.The Hadamard-Gate can be built from <a data-href="Rotation Gates" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/rotation-gates/rotation-gates.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Rotation Gates</a> like this: Since : With n-Hadamard gates on one can build an equal-weight superposition of all basis states on n qubits In general applying to an arbitrary basis state with the following holds:
,
with as the inner product of the n-bit strings Example:qc.h(qr[0]) # execute H-gate on qubit 0
]]></description><link>gates/single-qubit-gates/hadamard-gate.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Single-qubit gates/Hadamard-Gate.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 15:07:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Deutsch]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/deutsch.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/deutsch.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Deutsch.png</guid><pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 13:17:34 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="images/deutsch.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;images/deutsch.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[SWAP gate]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/swap-gate.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/swap-gate.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/SWAP gate.png</guid><pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 13:02:02 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Quantum Entanglement]]></title><description><![CDATA[If <a data-href="Product States" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Product States</a> are non-separable they are entangled. They can be semi entangled and fully entangled. All pure states that cannot be written as product states are entangled.Bell states are examples of entangled statesBell states are the simplest maximally entangled states. They form the Bell basis which is a four dimensional Hilbert Space for two qubits: ]]></description><link>quantum-mechanics/quantum-entanglement.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Quantum Entanglement.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 12:35:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Two-qubit gates]]></title><description><![CDATA[A two qubit gate is a Unitary U acting on 2 qubits.]]></description><link>gates/two-qubit-gates/two-qubit-gates.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Two-qubit gates/Two-qubit gates.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 12:27:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Gates]]></title><description><![CDATA[Gates are unitary operations a.k.a. matrices. Thus the direction of the circuit and equation are opposite.<img alt="Pasted image 20250716142535.png" src="images/pasted-image-20250716142535.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>gates/gates.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Gates.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 12:26:22 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250716142535]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/pasted-image-20250716142535.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/pasted-image-20250716142535.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Pasted image 20250716142535.png</guid><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 12:25:34 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Measurement]]></title><description><![CDATA[Single qubit measurements are a measurement of Z if not specified. Pauli measurements are projections into the eigenstates auf the Pauli Operator. It is also called measurement in the Z-basis or measurements in the computational basis.
The qubit wire ends with a measurement, unless a classical trigger is set with a classical bit from the measurement.<img alt="Measurement.png" src="images/measurement.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>gates/measurement.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Measurement.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 12:22:40 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="images/measurement.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;images/measurement.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Measurement]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/measurement.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/measurement.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Measurement.png</guid><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 12:19:28 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="images/measurement.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;images/measurement.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Single-qubit gates]]></title><description><![CDATA[For classical bits there is only one non-trivial gate, the NOT gate.
For qubits there are infinite possible gates. For example the <a data-href="Pauli Gates" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/pauli-gates/pauli-gates.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Pauli Gates</a>, the <a data-href="Hadamard-Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/hadamard-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Hadamard-Gate</a>, <a data-href="Phase-Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/phase-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Phase-Gate</a> and <a data-href="T-Gate" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/t-gate.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">T-Gate</a>.]]></description><link>gates/single-qubit-gates/single-qubit-gates.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Single-qubit gates/Single-qubit gates.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 12:12:38 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Bloch sphere]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/bloch-sphere.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/bloch-sphere.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Images/Bloch sphere.png</guid><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 12:09:18 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Quantum dynamics]]></title><description><![CDATA[The Quantum dynamics or time evolution of a quantum state is a map that evolves into also conserves probability because the time evolution operator U is unitary (): for any initial state . In quantum computation all unitary transformations are allowed and represent valid quantum operations.Examples:
Transformations generated by a control Hamiltonian like external control fields (e.g. electromagnetic fields)
Basic unitary transformation on single qubits, pairs of qubits and an ensemble on qubits are called <a data-href="Single-qubit gates" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/single-qubit-gates.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Single-qubit gates</a>, <a data-href="Two-qubit gates" href="gates/two-qubit-gates/two-qubit-gates.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Two-qubit gates</a> and <a data-href="n-qubit gates" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">n-qubit gates</a>. The Schrödinger equation is as follows (for time independent): with and ]]></description><link>quantum-mechanics/quantum-dynamics.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Quantum dynamics.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 14:13:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Ry Gate]]></title><description><![CDATA[The Ry Gate is one of the <a data-href="Rotation Gates" href="gates/single-qubit-gates/rotation-gates/rotation-gates.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Rotation Gates</a>. The Ry gate is a single-qubit rotation through angle &nbsp;(radians) around the y-axis.version 1.0
qubits 2
H q[0] # execute Hadamard gate on qubit 0
Ry q[0],1.78 # Rotation of 1.78 radians around the y-axis on qubit 0
]]></description><link>gates/single-qubit-gates/rotation-gates/ry-gate.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Gates/Single-qubit gates/Rotation Gates/Ry Gate.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 12:56:56 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>